(Music)
(موسيقى)
[Sanskrit]
(سنسكريتية)
This is an ode to the mother goddess,
هذه قصيدة للالهة الأم
that most of us in India learn when we are children.
يتعلمها معظمنا في الهند و نحن اطفال
I learned it when I was four
تعلمتها عندما كنت في الرابعة
at my mother's knee.
فوق حجر والدتي
That year she introduced me to dance,
في ذلك العام عرفتني على الرقص
and thus began
و هكذا بدأ
my tryst with classical dance.
عشقي للرقص الكلاسيكي
Since then -- it's been four decades now --
ومنذ ذلك الوقت --قد مضت اربعة عقود الان--
I've trained with the best in the field,
تدربت على يد الافضل في هذا المجال
performed across the globe,
أديت عروضا حول العالم
taught young and old alike,
علمت الشباب و الشيب على حد سواء
created, collaborated,
ألفت، تعاونت
choreographed,
صممت رقصات
and wove a rich tapestry
و نسجت لوحة جدارية غنية
of artistry, achievement and awards.
بالانجازات الفنية و الجوائز
The crowning glory was in 2007,
قمة المجد كانت عام 2007
when I received this country's
عندما حصلت على جائزة هذا البلد
fourth highest civilian award, the Padma Shri,
رابع اعلى جائزة وطنية (البادماشري)
for my contribution to art.
لمساهمتي للفن
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
But nothing, nothing prepared me
ولكن لاشيئ، لا شيئ أعدني
for what I was to hear
لما كنت سأسمع لاحقا
on the first of July 2008.
في الاول من يوليو عام 2008
I heard the word "carcinoma."
سمعت كلمة كارسينوما (سرطان)
Yes, breast cancer.
نعم سرطان الثدي
As I sat dumbstruck in my doctor's office,
اثناء جلوسي مذهولة في مكتب طبيبي
I heard other words:
سمعت كلمات اخري
"cancer," "stage," "grade."
سرطان مرحلة مستوى
Until then, Cancer was the zodiac
حتى ذلك الوقت كان السرطان يعني البرج
sign of my friend,
الفلكي لصديقتي
stage was what I performed on,
المرحلة (المسرح) ما أؤدي عليه
and grades were what I got in school.
و مستويات هي ماحصلت عليه في المدرسة
That day, I realized
ذلك اليوم ادركت
I had an unwelcome, uninvited,
انني سأحظى بشريك غير مرحب به
new life partner.
غير مدعو، جديد
As a dancer,
كراقصة
I know the nine rasas or the navarasas:
كنت اعرف الاصول التسعة او ما يسمى بالنافاراساس
anger, valor,
الغضب، البسالة
disgust, humor
الاشمئزاز، المرح
and fear.
و الخوف
I thought I knew what fear was.
ظننت انني اعلم ما الخوف
That day, I learned what fear was.
في ذلك اليوم، تعلمت ماهو الخوف
Overcome with the enormity of it all
مقهورة بسبب فداحة الامر
and the complete feeling of loss of control,
و الاحساس التام بقلة الحيلة
I shed copious tears
ذرفت الكثير من الدموع
and asked my dear husband, Jayant.
وسألت زوجي العزيز، جيانت
I said, "Is this it? Is this the end of the road?
قلت: هل هذا هو كل مافي الامر؟ هل هذه نهاية الطريق؟
Is this the end of my dance?"
هل هذه نهاية رقصتي؟
And he, the positive soul that he is,
وهو بروحه وايجابيته المعهودة
said, "No, this is just a hiatus,
قال: كلا، هذه مجرد استراحة
a hiatus during the treatment,
استراحة خلال فترة العلاج
and you'll get back to doing what you do best."
وستعودين لممارسة ما تبرعين به
I realized then
ادركت عندها
that I, who thought I had complete control of my life,
انني، من ظننت ان لي سيطرة كاملة على حياتي
had control of only three things:
اسيطر فقط على ثلاثة اشياء:
My thought, my mind --
فكري، عقلي
the images that these thoughts created --
ماتخلقه تلك الافكار من صور
and the action that derived from it.
و الافعال المستمدة منها
So here I was wallowing
وها انا ذا اتخبط
in a vortex of emotions
في دوامة من المشاعر
and depression and what have you,
والاكتئاب وما الى ذلك
with the enormity of the situation,
من فداحة الامر
wanting to go to a place of healing, health and happiness.
راغبة في الذهاب الى مكان حيث الشفاء، الصحة و السعادة
I wanted to go from where I was
اردت ان اذهب من حيث كنت
to where I wanted to be,
الى حيث اردت ان اكون
for which I needed something.
كنت بحاجة الى شيئ
I needed something that would pull me out of all this.
احتجت الى شيئ ينتزعني من كل هذا.
So I dried my tears,
لذا جففت دموعي
and I declared to the world at large ...
و أعلنتها للعالم كافة
I said, "Cancer's only one page in my life,
قلت: ان السرطان ليس الا صفحة في حياتي
and I will not allow this page to impact the rest of my life."
و لن ادع هذه الصفحة تؤثر في باقي حياتي
I also declared to the world at large
كما اعلنت للعالم ايضا
that I would ride it out,
انني سأقود السرطان خارجا
and I would not allow cancer to ride me.
ولن ادعه يقودني
But to go from where I was
ولكن للذهاب من حيث كنت
to where I wanted to be,
الى حيث اردت ان اكون
I needed something.
كنت احتاج شيئا
I needed an anchor, an image,
احتاج الى مرساة، الى رمز
a peg
الى وتد
to peg this process on,
لادعم به هذه العملية
so that I could go from there.
فاستطيع ان انطلق من هناك
And I found that in my dance,
ووجدت ذلك في رقصي
my dance, my strength, my energy, my passion,
رقصي هو قوتي طاقتي شغفي
my very life breath.
الهواء الذي اتنفسه
But it wasn't easy.
ولكن لم يكن ذلك سهل
Believe me, it definitely wasn't easy.
صدقونى حتما لم يكن بالامر الهين
How do you keep cheer
كيف تبقى مبتهجا
when you go from beautiful
عندما تتحول من الجمال
to bald in three days?
الى الصلع في ثلاثة ايام
How do you not despair
كيف لا تيأس
when, with the body ravaged by chemotherapy,
و جسمك قد دمره العلاج الكيميائي
climbing a mere flight of stairs was sheer torture,
بحيث يتحول صعود الدرج الى رحلة من العذاب
that to someone like me who could dance for three hours?
لشخص مثلي كان يمكنه الرقص لثلاث ساعات؟
How do you not get overwhelmed
كيف لا يغمرك
by the despair and the misery of it all?
اليأس و البؤس من كل هذا؟
All I wanted to do was curl up and weep.
كل ما ردت فعله هو ان انزوي وابكي
But I kept telling myself fear and tears
ولكن ظللت اخبر نفسي ان الخوف و الدموع
are options I did not have.
خياران لم احظى بهما
So I would drag myself into my dance studio --
لذا كنت اسحب نفسي الى استوديو الرقص
body, mind and spirit -- every day into my dance studio,
اضع جسدي عقلي و روحي كل يوم داخل استوديو الرقص خاصتي
and learn everything I learned
و اتعلم كل ما تعلمته
when I was four, all over again,
عندما كنت في الرابعة من جديد
reworked, relearned, regrouped.
اعدت كل ما عملته وتعلمته و جمعته
It was excruciatingly painful, but I did it.
لقد كان الالم فظيعا ولكنني فعلتها
Difficult.
صعب
I focused on my mudras,
ركزت على حركاتي (المودراس)
on the imagery of my dance,
على تخيلات رقصي
on the poetry and the metaphor
على الشعر و الاستعارة
and the philosophy of the dance itself.
و فلسفة الرقص في حد ذاته
And slowly, I moved out
و ببطء انتقلت
of that miserable state of mind.
من تلك الحالة النفسية البائسة
But I needed something else.
ولكنني كنت بحاجة الى شيئ اخر
I needed something to go that extra mile,
احتجت لشيئ لاستطيع ان ابذل ذلك الجهد الاضافي
and I found it in that metaphor
ثم وجدتها في تلك الاستعارة
which I had learned from my mother when I was four.
التي تعلمتها من والدتي عندما كنت في الرابعة
The metaphor of Mahishasura Mardhini,
استعارة ماهيش ماهاتميا
of Durga.
لدورغا
Durga, the mother goddess, the fearless one,
دورغا، الالهة الام، التي لا تعرف الخوف
created by the pantheon of Hindu gods.
انشاها الهة الهندوس
Durga, resplendent, bedecked, beautiful,
دورغا متألقة مكللة جميلة
her 18 arms
باذرعها الثمانية عشر
ready for warfare,
مستعدة للحرب
as she rode astride her lion
ممتطية اسدها
into the battlefield to destroy Mahishasur.
في ساحة المعركة لتدمر ماهيشاسور
Durga, the epitome
دورغا، مثال
of creative feminine energy,
الطاقة النسائية الخلاقة
or shakti.
او شاكتي
Durga, the fearless one.
دورغا التي لا تعرف الخوف
I made that image of Durga
اخذت تلك الصورة لدورغا
and her every attribute, her every nuance,
بكل سماتها ووضوحها
my very own.
وجعلتها لي
Powered by the symbology of a myth
مدفوعة برمزية الأسطورة
and the passion of my training,
و شغفي للتدريب
I brought laser-sharp focus into my dance,
ركزت بحدة شديدة على رقصي
laser-sharp focus to such an extent
ركزت بشدة لدرجة
that I danced a few weeks after surgery.
انني رقصت بعد اسابيع قليلة من العملية الجراحية
I danced through chemo and radiation cycles,
رقصت خلال دورات العلاج الكيميائي و الاشعاعي
much to the dismay of my oncologist.
مما اثار هلع معالج الاورام لدي
I danced between chemo and radiation cycles
رقصت بين دورات العلاج الكيميائي و الاشعاعي
and badgered him to fit it
و ألححت عليه ليوفق بينها
to my performing dance schedule.
و بين برنامجي للرقص
What I had done
و ما فعلته
is I had tuned out of cancer
هو انني قلبت موجتي من السرطان
and tuned into my dance.
الى رقصي
Yes, cancer has just been one page in my life.
نعم، كان السرطان صفحة واحدة في حياتي
My story
قصتي
is a story of overcoming setbacks,
هي قصة عن التغلب على العقبات
obstacles and challenges
الصعاب و التحديات
that life throws at you.
التي تلقيها عليك الحياة
My story is the power of thought.
قصتي هي عن قوة العقل
My story is the power of choice.
قصتي هي عن قوة الاختيار
It's the power of focus.
قوة التفكير
It's the power of bringing ourselves
هي القدرة على صرف
to the attention of something that so animates you,
انتباهنا الى شيئ يفعمنا بالحياة
so moves you,
يدفعنا بقوة
that something even like cancer becomes insignificant.
فيصبح شيئ ما كالسرطان غير ذو اهمية
My story is the power of a metaphor.
قصتي هي قوة الاستعارة
It's the power of an image.
القوة وراء صورة معينة
Mine was that of Durga,
صورتي كانت لدورغا
Durga the fearless one.
دورغا التي لاتعرف الخوف
She was also called Simhanandini,
عرفت ايضا بسيمهانانديني
the one who rode the lion.
التي امتطت الاسد
As I ride out,
كما نجوت
as I ride my own inner strength,
ممتطيًتا قوتي الباطنية
my own inner resilience,
مرونتي الباطنية
armed as I am with what medication can provide
مسلحتًا بما توفره الادوية
and continue treatment,
وواصلت العلاج
as I ride out into the battlefield of cancer,
كما لو انني اتوجه الى ساحة معركة السرطان
asking my rogue cells to behave,
طالبة من خلاياي المارقة (السرطانية) ان تحسن التصرف
I want to be known not as a cancer survivor,
اريد ان أعرف ليس كناجية من السرطان
but as a cancer conqueror.
بل كقاهرة للسرطان
I present to you an excerpt of that work
اقدم لكم مقتطفًا من ذلك العمل
"Simhanandini."
"سيماهنانديني"
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
(Music)
(موسيقى)